William Howard Taft IV Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Howard Taft IV Papers 1958-1989 1970-1989
MSS77559
Taft, William Howard, IV, 1945-
29,750 items
85 containers
34 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer and government official. Personal and family correspondence, official correspondence, memoranda, speeches and writings, and daily records chiefly documenting Taft's government service in the Richard M. Nixon, Gerald R. Ford, and Ronald Reagan presidential administrations.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Addabbo, Joseph Patrick, 1925-1986--Correspondence.; Aspin, Les--Correspondence.; Barnes, Chaplin B.--Correspondence.; Bell, Terrel H. (Terrel Howard), 1921-1996--Correspondence.; Brennan, Peter J., 1918- --Correspondence.; Brooks, Jack, 1922-2012--Correspondence.; Brown, Jonathan C. (Jonathan Charles), 1942- --Correspondence.; Carlucci, Frank Charles, 1930-2018--Correspondence.; Cavanaugh, James H. (James Henry), 1937- --Correspondence.; Cohn, Samuel M. (Samuel Maurice), 1915-2005--Correspondence.; Cutler, Lloyd N.--Correspondence.; Everett, Robinson O.--Correspondence.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Helm, Lewis M., 1931- --Correspondence.; Horowitz, Michael--Correspondence.; Laffer, Arthur B.--Correspondence.; Long, Russell B.--Correspondence.; Manning, Helen Taft, 1891-1987--Correspondence.; Mathews, Forrest David, 1935- --Correspondence.; Morrill, William A. (William Ashley), 1930- --Correspondence.; Nader, Ralph.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; O'Neill, Tip--Correspondence.; Perle, Richard Norman, 1941- --Correspondence.; Powell, Colin L.--Correspondence.; Price, Melvin, 1905-1988--Correspondence.; Reagan, Ronald.; Richardson, Elliot L., 1920-1999--Correspondence.; Roth, William V., Jr. (William Victor), 1921-2003--Correspondence.; Schoonmaker, John Derek--Correspondence.; Schroeder, Pat--Correspondence.; Smith, Carl R. (Carl Richard), 1933- --Correspondence.; Smith, Edward Byron, 1944- --Correspondence.; Stillman, Peter G.--Correspondence.; Stockman, David Alan, 1946- --Correspondence.; Super, Charles M.--Correspondence.; Taft family.; Taft, Barbara Hoult Bradfield, 1917- --Correspondence.; Taft, John Thomas, 1950- --Correspondence.; Taft, Julia Vadala--Correspondence.; Taft, Robert, Jr., 1917-1993--Correspondence.; Taft, William Howard, 1915-1991--Correspondence.; Taft, William Howard, IV, 1945-; Thayer, W. Paul, 1919- --Correspondence.; Thurmond, Strom, 1902-2003--Correspondence.; Tower, John G. (John Goodwin), 1925-1991--Correspondence.; Weinberger, Caspar W.; Weinberger, Caspar W.--Correspondence.; Wright, Joseph Robert, 1938- --Correspondence.
Organizations
Council of Economic Advisers (U.S.); Domestic Council (U.S.); Leva, Hawes, Symington, Martin and Oppenheimer.; United States. Department of Defense.; United States. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare.; United States. Federal Trade Commission.; United States. Office of Management and Budget.
Subjects
Entitlement spending--United States.; Executive impoundment of appropriated funds--United States.; Influenza vaccines.; National health insurance--United States.; Negative income tax--United States.; Older people--United States.; Practice of law--Washington (D.C.); Public welfare--United States.; Revenue sharing--United States.; School integration--United States.; Swine influenza.; Tax and expenditure limitations--United States.; Taxation--United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--United States.
Places
United States--Appropriations and expenditures.; United States--Armed Forces--Appropriations and expenditures.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.
Occupations
Lawyers.; Public officials.
Acquisition Information
The papers of William Howard Taft IV (1945- ), lawyer and government official, were deposited in the Library of Congress in 1989 by Taft.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Material
Papers of Charles P. Taft, Robert Taft, Jr., Robert Alphonso Taft, William Howard Taft III, and President William H. Taft, great uncle, uncle, grandfather, father, and great grandfather of William Howard Taft IV, are also in the custody of the Library.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1945, Sept. 13 Born, Washington, D.C.
1966 Graduated, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1968 1970 Federal Trade Commission Investigation Project
1969 Graduated, Harvard Law School, Cambridge, Mass.
1969 1970 Attorney-advisor to chairman, Federal Trade Commission
1970 Principal assistant to deputy director, Office of Management and Budget
1970 1972 Executive assistant to director, Office of Management and Budget
1973 1976 Executive assistant to secretary, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare
1974 Married Julia Vadala
1976 1977 General counsel, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare
1977 1981 Partner at Leva, Hawes, Symington, Martin & Oppenheimer, Washington, D.C.
1981 1984 General counsel, Defense Department
1984 1989 Deputy secretary, Defense Department
1989 1992 Permanent representative, North Atlantic Treaty Organization
1992 Partner, Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver and Jacobson, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Howard Taft IV (1945- ) span the years 1958-1989, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1970-1989 when he served in the presidential administrations of Richard Nixon, Gerald Ford, and Ronald Reagan in postings at the Federal Trade Commission, Office of Management and Budget, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, and Department of Defense. The papers are organized in General Correspondence, Government File, and Miscellany series.
The General Correspondence series includes correspondence with family members Barbara Bradfield Hoult Taft (mother), William Howard Taft III (father), Julia Vadala Taft (wife), John Thomas Taft (brother), Robert Taft, Jr. (uncle), and Helen Taft Manning (great aunt), daughter of president William H. Taft. Also in the General Correspondence are personal letters to and from friends and colleagues, including Chaplin B. Barnes, Jonathan C. Brown, Lloyd N. Cutler, Richard Norman Perle, John Derek Schoonmaker, Edward Byron Smith, Jr., Peter G. Stillman, Charles M. Super, Paul Thayer, and Caspar W. Weinberger.
The Government File, the largest series in the collection, is arranged into Federal Trade Commission (FTC), Office of Management and Budget (OMB), Department of Health Education and Welfare (HEW), and Department of Defense (DOD) subseries documenting Taft's government service. The OMB and HEW subseries consist mainly of chronologically arranged official correspondence, memoranda, and other daily records. The DoD subseries includes a large chronological file of official correspondence, memoranda, and other daily records. The files from OMB, HEW, and DOD complement the General Correspondence.
Taft's government service started in 1970 at the Federal Trade Commission during the Nixon administration. From 1968 to 1970 he participated in a project initiated by consumer advocate Ralph Nader to probe the effectiveness of the Federal Trade Commission. The new chairman of the commission, Caspar W. Weinberger, on reading a study produced by the FTC Investigation Project, asked Nader if any of the project staff were qualified for service with the commission. Nader recommended Taft, and he was named attorney-advisor to Weinberger. This appointment was the start of a long professional relationship between the two. Material related to the FTC Investigation Project and Taft's attorney-advisor tenure comprise the Federal Trade Commission file of the Government series.
The bulk of the material in the Office of Management and Budget subseries parallels the period 1970-1973 during the Nixon administration, when Taft worked as Weinberger's principal executive assistant while the latter was deputy director and director of OMB. Subjects of memoranda to Weinberger and others include meeting agendas of the Domestic Council and the Council of Economic Advisors, federal-state revenue sharing, guidelines for drafting legislation, projections on the effects of an aging population on entitlement programs, presidential impoundment of appropriated funds, tax expenditure analysis, the defense budget, and the "peace dividend" occasioned by the withdrawal of American troops from Vietnam. Other participants in OMB internal communication include Samuel M. Cohn and Arthur B. Laffer.
During 1973, Taft served as Caspar Weinberger's executive assistant when Weinberger held the dual offices of secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare and counselor to the president for human resources during Nixon's second term. There is substantial material in the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare subseries on the scope, purpose, and activities of the newly-created office of counselor to the president for human resources. Weinberger continued to serve as secretary of HEW until 1975, early in the Ford administration, and Taft continued as his executive assistant. During 1976-1977, Taft was general counsel, or chief lawyer, for HEW under secretary Forrest David Mathews. Recurring topics in the HEW subseries include welfare reform, the negative income tax, school desegregation cases, swine flu vaccine liability, and national health insurance. Internal and external correspondents besides Weinberger and Mathews include Terrel Howard Bell, Peter J. Brennan, Frank Charles Carlucci, James H. Cavanaugh, Lewis M. Helm, Russell B. Long, William A. Morrill, Elliot L. Richardson, Pat Schroeder, and Julia Vadala (Taft).
Between 1981 and 1989, Taft was successively general counsel and deputy secretary of the Defense Department under secretaries of defense Caspar Weinberger and Frank Charles Carlucci during the Reagan presidential administration. The Department of Defense (DoD) file documenting Taft's service in this agency is the largest subseries of the Government series. It consists mainly of official outgoing correspondence with attached correspondence and other daily records arranged chronologically and inventoried by addressee, subject, and control number. Frequent correspondents besides the secretaries of defense include Joseph Patrick Addabbo, Les Aspin, Jack Brooks, Robinson O. Everett, Michael Horowitz, Tip O'Neill, Richard Norman Perle, Colin L. Powell, Melvin Price, William V. Roth, Carl R. Smith, David Alan Stockman, W. Paul Thayer, Strom Thurmond, John G. Tower, and Joseph Robert Wright.
The most numerous document types in the Miscellany series are records related to Taft's law partnership with the Washington firm of Leva, Hawes, Symington, Martin and Oppenheimer and writings not related to his governmental duties, such as college term papers. Speeches and writings resulting from his official duties are housed in the Government File ewith the files of the appropriate governmental entity. For example, a speeches and writings file of Taft material is part of the DOD subseries of the Government File.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in three series:
General Correspondence, 1960-1989
Government File, 1958-1989
Miscellany, 1960-1988
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1960-1989 (Box 1-3)
  Letters sent and received with attached and related material.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1960-1970, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1971-1986, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1987-1989, undated, (6 folders) (Box 3)
- Government File, 1958-1989 (Box 4-74)
  - Department of Defense, 1981-1989 (Box 4-66)
    Chronological office files, correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches, articles, telephone logs, and miscellaneous material.
    Arranged by type of material or topic and thereunder chronologically. A master inventory of the chronological office file precedes the documents. The inventory and file are organized chronologically on a monthly basis, and pertinent copies of the inventory are filed with each monthly segment. Most of the chronological office files are arranged into Sets I and II established by the donor.
    - Center for Strategic and International Studies, Georgetown University, Washington, D.C., 1984-1986 (Box 4)
    - Chronological file
      - 1981
        - Annual inventory
        - January-March, (5 folders)
        - April
          - Nos. 1-46, (2 folders)
          - Nos. 47-108, (2 folders) (Box 5)
        - May
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - June
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 6)
        - July
          - Set I
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - August
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - September (Box 7)
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
        - October
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - November (Box 8)
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
        - December
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
      - 1982
        - Annual inventory
        - January (Box 9)
          - Set I
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - February
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
        - March
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-39, (2 folders)
            - Nos. 40-63 (Box 10)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - April
          - Set I
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - May
          - Set I
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 11)
        - June
          - Set I
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - July
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
            - Nos. 1-23
            - Nos. 24-55 (Box 12)
        - August
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - September
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - October (Box 13)
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
        - November
          - Set I
          - Set II
        - December
          - Set I
          - Set II
      - 1983 (Box 14)
        - Annual inventory
        - January
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - February
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - March (Box 15)
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - April
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-34, (2 folders)
            - Nos. 35-45 (Box 16)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - May
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - June (Box 17)
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - July
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - August
          - Set I
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 18)
        - September
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - October
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-28
            - Nos. 29-47 (Box 19)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - November
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - December
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-16
            - Nos. 17-27 (Box 20)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
      - 1984
        - Annual inventory
        - January
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-62, (2 folders)
            - Nos. 63-103 (Box 21)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - February
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
            - Nos. 1-42
            - Nos. 43-67 (Box 22)
        - March
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - April
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-32
            - Nos. 33-58 (Box 23)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - May
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II
            - Nos. 1-29
            - Nos. 30-63 (Box 24)
        - June
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - July
          - Set I
            - Nos. 33-47, (2 folders)
            - Nos. 48-83 (Box 25)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - August
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - September (Box 26)
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - October
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - November
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 27)
        - December
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
      - 1985
        - Annual inventory
        - January
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 28)
        - February
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II
        - March
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-65, (2 folders)
            - Nos. 66-95 (Box 29)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
          - Set III, (2 folders)
        - April
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders) (Box 30)
        - May
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II
            - Nos. 1-56
            - Nos. 57-95 (Box 31)
        - June
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - July
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders) (Box 32)
        - August
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - September
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-30
            - Nos. 31-51 (Box 33)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - October
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - November (Box 34)
          - Set I
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - December
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
            - Nos. 1-22
            - Nos. 23-55 (Box 35)
      - 1986
        - Annual inventory
        - January
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - February
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 36)
        - March
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - April (Box 37)
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - May
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 38)
        - June
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
        - July
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 39)
        - August
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - September
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders) (Box 40)
        - October
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II
            - Nos. 1-57
            - Nos. 58-87 (Box 41)
        - November
          - Set I
          - Set II
        - December
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
      - 1987
        - Annual inventory
        - January (Box 42)
          - Set I
          - Set II
        - February
          - Set I
          - Set II
        - March
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 43)
          - Set III, (2 folders)
          - Set IV, (2 folders)
        - April
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-20
            - Nos. 21-62 (Box 44)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - May
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders) (Box 45)
        - June
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - July (Box 46)
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - August
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
            - Nos. 1-26
            - Nos. 27-90, (2 folders) (Box 47)
        - September
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - October (Box 48)
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - November
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders) (Box 49)
        - December
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
      - 1988 (Box 50)
        - Annual inventory
        - January
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - February
          - Set I
            - Nos. 1-61, (2 folders)
            - Nos. 62-87 (Box 51)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - March
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - April (Box 52)
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - May
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set II
            - Nos. 1-47
            - Nos. 48-108, (2 folders) (Box 53)
        - June
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (3 folders)
        - July (Box 54)
          - Set I, (3 folders)
          - Set II, (2 folders)
        - August
          - Set I, (2 folders)
          - Set 2, (3 folders) (Box 55)
        - September, (4 folders)
        - October-November, (8 folders) (Box 56)
        - December, (5 folders) (Box 57)
      - 1989
        - Jan. 3-23, (3 folders)
        - Jan. 24-31, (2 folders) (Box 58)
        - Feb., (7 folders)
        - Mar.-Apr., (8 folders) (Box 59)
    - Ditchley conference, Ditchley Park, Oxfordshire, England, 1982 (Box 60)
    - Speeches and writings
      - General counsel
        - Articles, 1983
        - Speeches, 1981-1983, (4 folders)
      - Deputy secretary of defense speech file
        - Master inventory, 1984-1989
        - 24 Jan.-11 May 1984, (4 folders)
        - 15 May 1984-28 Mar. 1985, (7 folders) (Box 61)
        - 4 Apr. 1985-26 Feb. 1986, (7 folders) (Box 62)
        - 27 Feb. 1986-18 Feb. 1987, (6 folders) (Box 63)
        - 6 Mar. 1987-29 June 1988, (9 folders) (Box 64)
        - 18 July 1988-11 Apr. 1989, (3 folders) (Box 65)
    - Telephone logs
      - 1983-1987, (3 folders)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 66)
    - Travel, 1984-1988, (5 folders)
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1971-1978 (Box 67-70)
    Memoranda, correspondence, reports, studies, speeches, notes, and miscellaneous material.
    - Nov. 1972-Dec. 1974, (8 folders) (Box 67)
    - Jan. 1975-June 1976, (7 folders) (Box 68)
    - July 1976-Nov. 1976, (6 folders) (Box 69)
    - Dec. 1976-Aug. 1978, undated, (6 folders) (Box 70)
  - Federal Trade Commission, 1968-1970 (Box 71)
    Correspondence, memoranda, reports, statements, clippings, notes, and miscellaneous material.
    - Investigation Project, 1968-1969, undated, (2 folders) (Box 71)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970, undated
  - Office of Management and Budget, 1970-1974 (Box 71-72)
    Correspondence, memoranda, studies, and miscellaneous material.
    - 1970-1971, (3 folders)
    - 1972-1974, (6 folders) (Box 72)
  - Presidential Transition (1980), 1958-1981 (Box 72-74)
    Studies, reports, memoranda, proposals, and miscellaneous material.
    Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
    - Department of Defense (Box 72)
      - Background material
        - Canby, Steven L., William S. Lind, Edward N. Luttwak, Norman Polmar, and Pierre M. Sprey, "Alternative Analysis of the State of U.S. General Purpose Forces: The Need to Restructure for Combat Effectiveness," circa 1980
        - Miscellaneous, 1958-1980 (Box 73)
        - Taft, Robert, Jr., Gary Hart, and William S. Lind, "White Paper on Defense," 1978